Hi, I’m Gina.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you can learn how to answer
job interview questions in English.
Have you ever had a job interview in English?
If English is not your first language, answering
job interview questions in English can add
stress to the experience.
However, there are some simple, effective
tips you can use to give better answers to
job interview questions in clear, natural
English.
You’ll learn about these tips and tricks
during this lesson!
You’ll see eight common job interview questions
and four different techniques you can use.
You’ll see how to answer these common job
interview questions, using the techniques
we’ll show you.
Let’s start with our eight common job interview
questions.
Tell me a little about yourself.
Where do you see yourself five years from
now?
What are your strengths/weaknesses?
What is your leadership style?
Can you tell me about a time when you demonstrated
----?
when you demonstrated strong leadership?
Or, can you tell me about a time when you
demonstrated excellent customer service?
Tell me about a time you dealt with a challenging
situation at work.
Why do you want this job?
Why should we hire you?
What does concise mean?
It means that you don’t waste words.
If you speak concisely, you get right to the
point and don’t add anything unnecessary
to your answer.
Let’s look at two questions in this section:
Tell me a little about yourself.
Where do you see yourself five years from
now?
These are very common job interview questions,
and they’re also very open questions.
Open questions can be dangerous.
Do you know why?
It’s because you might ramble.
Ramble means to talk a lot without saying
much.
This won’t give the interviewer a good impression!
Let’s start by looking at a sample answer
to the question tell me a little about yourself.
Well, I was born in a small town in northern
Italy, where I also went to school.
I studied engineering at university and then…
So, after I graduated…
I mean, I did a master’s degree first, but
then I worked for a small firm in my hometown
for a few years, which was great fun.
After that…
Okay, we can stop there.
Do you think this is a good answer?
Why or why not?
It’s not a very good answer.
Why not?
There are three things the candidate does
which you should try to avoid:
One: the candidate includes lots of unnecessary
details.
Two: he doesn’t speak in full sentences.
Three: he doesn’t have any clear direction.
If you do these things, your answer to this
answer will be long and unfocused.
What’s the solution?
You need to be more concise.
But how?
First, avoid unnecessary details.
Don’t give your entire work history; the
interviewers can get that from your CV if
they want it.
Secondly, speak in full sentences with a clear
beginning and end.
This means you need to be thinking ahead while
you speak.
Thirdly, think about what you want to highlight
in your answer, and put it at the beginning.
This will give your answer a clear direction.
Let’s look at some examples of this:
I’ve always loved designing and building
things, so I suppose it’s natural that I
became an engineer.
I’ve worked in a variety of roles and companies,
which I’ve learned a lot from, but now I’m
ready for a new challenge.
What do you think?
Better?
It’s much better.
Let's look at the start.
Immediately, the candidate identifies a key
feature (he loves designing and building things),
and links it to his engineering career.
The candidate’s answer is very concise:
there are no unnecessary details, and it also
has a clear end.
What about our second question?
Here’s one possible answer:
There are many things I could be doing.
I’d like to have, you know, some sort of
progress…
What I mean is that I don’t just want to
be doing the same things I’m doing now.
I like to be moving forward in my career,
for example…
Err…
I definitely see myself in a better position
than I am now.
Good answer?
Bad answer?
Okay, it’s not terrible, but it could be
much better.
The candidate is rambling.
She doesn’t make her point clear, she doesn’t
speak in full sentences, and she wastes words
on unclear and unnecessary ideas.
Here’s a better answer:
I don’t know exactly, but the most important
thing is that I continue to learn and grow
in my career.
I’m the kind of person who needs new challenges
to stay focused.
I might even start my own business, because
that’s something I’ve always wanted to
do at some point in my life.
This is much more concise.
The candidate’s answer has a clear beginning
and end, and doesn’t waste words.
So, what can you do to make your answers more
concise?
The best way to practise is to record yourself
speaking.
You could record yourself answering these
two questions.
Then, listen to yourself.
Try to find sentences which you don’t finish,
or words which don’t add anything to your
meaning.
Then, try again.
Keep practising until your answer is clean
and focused.
Next, let’s look at another point which
will make your answers clearer and more structured:
signposting language.
Signposting language means words and phrases
which show your listener where you’re going.
For example, the words ‘for example’ are
signposting language.
When I say for example, you know I’m about
to give you an example.
Simple, right?
Yes, but it’s also very important.
Without signposting language, longer answers
can lose focus and be hard to follow.
You’ll see answers to two questions in this
section:
What are your strengths and weaknesses?
What is your leadership style?
Let’s look at a sample answer to the first
question.
I’m very good at working with other people.
In my last job, I always tried to encourage
my colleagues and create a good atmosphere.
I suppose I can be a little bit careless sometimes.
I’m not the kind of person who focuses on
details.
I’m very calm, and I can keep a cool head in very stressful situations.
What do you think?
It’s not bad, but it could be hard to follow.
The candidate jumps around a lot.
Adding signposting language can make a big
difference.
Let’s see how.
Notice that the content is exactly the same.
We haven’t changed the candidate’s basic
ideas at all.
However, the answer is now much clearer and
easier to follow.
Using signposting language like this can make
a big difference!
Let’s look at our second question for this
section.
What is your leadership style?
Look at a sample answer which doesn’t use
signposting language.
I’m quite a hands-off manager.
If one of my team has a project, I’ll keep
an eye on things, but I don’t need to be
involved in every detail.
I’m very approachable.
I make sure my team know they can come to
me with problems or questions at any time.
I like to lead from the front.
If everyone’s working late to meet a deadline,
I make sure I’m there with them.
Now, look at some signposting language you
could use in this answer.
Now, you have a job to do!
I want you to pause the video and put these
signposting phrases into the answer you just
saw.
Go on, pause the video and do it now!
Ready?
Let’s look at the answers:
How did you do?
Were you able to use the signposting language?
Remember, signposting language might seem
very simple, but don’t forget about it.
Using signposting language well makes your
answers much clearer and easier to follow.
Now, let’s look at another way to make
your answers more structured, clearer and
more focused.
You’ll see answers to these two questions
in this section.
Can you tell me about a time when you demonstrated
-----?
Tell me about a time you dealt with a challenging
situation at work.
These questions are likely to need longer
answers.
With longer answers, it’s really important
that your answers have a clear structure.
Otherwise, your meaning might get lost!
There’s a method you can use here; it’s
called the STAR method.
STAR means situation, task, action, result.
So, you start your answer by giving the context:
what was the situation, and what did you have
to do?
Then, you talk about what you actually did,
and what the end result was.
Let’s do an example together.
Can you tell me about a time when you demonstrated
excellent customer service?
Let’s use the STAR method.
There was one time when a customer’s order
hadn’t arrived, and we didn’t know what
had happened to it.
The customer was very unhappy, and I had to
try to solve the problem for him.
I arranged for a replacement to be sent, thinking
we could find out what happened to the previous
order later.
In the end, the customer was happy that I
could solve his problem quickly and simply.
You see how following this method lets you
build clear, structured answers?
situation,
task,
action,
result
Let’s do another example.
Think about our second question.
Tell me about a time you dealt with a challenging
situation at work.
This time, you’re going to try!
Pause the video and make an answer to this
question.
Your answer should be four sentences long.
Follow the STAR method, one sentence for each
part.
How was that?
Did you find it easy to make your own answer?
Let’s look at one way you could answer this
question.
Once, we realised three days before a project
deadline that two of our teams were using
incompatible software tools.
As the project manager, I had to find a way
to deal with this without causing any delays.
I talked to both team leaders and we made
a plan for one team to convert their work
into a different format, with help from some
staff from other departments.
It was very close but we managed to get everything
done on time.
Again, you can see the STAR method in action:
situation,
task,
action,
result.
If you combine this STAR method with the signposting
language you learned about in part two, you’ll
be able to express yourself clearly in English,
even in longer and more complex answers.
Finally, let’s look at another tip you can
use to impress your interviewer and increase
your chances of getting that job offer!
You’re going to learn about mirroring and
how it can help you.
What does mirroring mean?
It means using some of the same words and
expressions as the person you’re talking
to.
For example, if the interviewer asks you:
How do you think your values fit our company
culture?
You could start your answer by saying:
I think my values are a good fit for your
company culture for two reasons.
One…
Mirroring has several benefits.
First, it keeps your answers focused.
By using the same words and phrases, your
answer will be relevant.
More importantly, it shows the interviewer
that you’re listening and that you care
about the questions and the company.
Mirroring is powerful.
We unconsciously mirror people when we like
or respect them.
Using mirroring consciously will help you
to make a better impression.
You should start by researching the company
you’re applying to.
How do they describe themselves?
What adjectives do they use on their website
or in their advertising?
Also, read the job advertisement carefully.
Pay attention to the words they use to describe
the candidate they’re looking for.
Use these words in your answers.
Let’s think about this question:
Why do you want this job?
Imagine you’re applying to a company which
describes itself as ‘innovative’ and ‘forward-looking’.
In the job advertisement, they say they want
someone who is ‘creative’ and ‘flexible’.
Here’s a good sample answer:
Creativity is very important to me, and I’ve
always wanted to work in an environment where
I can innovate and find my own solutions to
challenges.
I also feel that your company will continue
to evolve in the future, and I like the idea
of contributing to that development.
The candidate doesn’t use all four words,
but she does reference all four ideas.
For example, instead of ‘forward-looking’,
she talks about the company evolving in the
future.
In this way, she shows that she’s in tune
with the company’s values.
Let’s do one more example.
Imagine you’re applying to a company which
describes itself as ‘commanding respect’
and which talks with pride about its long
history.
In the job advertisement, they say they want
someone who has ‘great communication skills’
and ‘passion for helping others’.
During the interview, they ask:
Why should we hire you?
Here’s a good sample answer, using mirroring.
I believe that great customer service starts
with good communication, which is a strength
of mine.
I also think that in customer service, you
need to care about what you’re doing.
I care about helping others and as such I
believe you would find me to be a respectful
and effective team member who can fit with
the established traditions of your company.
Again, the candidate doesn’t necessarily
use the words directly, but he does reference
all four of the ideas.
Be careful if you use mirroring; you don’t
want to sound like a robot!
This is why you sometimes need to change words
and phrases slightly, instead of repeating
them again and again.
Now, you’ve seen four effective techniques
you can use to give better answers to job
interview questions in English.
Remember: be concise, use signposting language,
use the STAR method to structure longer answers,
and mirror key words and phrases.
We hope it was useful.
Good luck if you have a job interview coming
up soon!
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!